Guide to the Tamiment Library Poster and Broadside Collection GRAPHICS.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library Poster and Broadside Collection
1904-2019
1970-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
GRAPHICS.002
4.5 Linear Feet
The Tamiment Library Poster Collection consists of items published between 1904 and 2019, that relate to left-radicalism, progressive movements, labor unions, and counter-culture in the United States, and in over thirty other countries. With new additions being received on a regular basis, the collection can be expected to grow well beyond its present size of 2,165 posters and broadsides.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2017.051, NPA.1990.008, NPA.1993.013, NPA.1993.022, NPA.1993.023, NPA.1997.012, NPA.2000.223, NPA.2001.064, NPA.2001.066, NPA.2001.076, NPA.2001.079, NPA.2003.094, NPA.2005.025, NPA.2005.072, NPA.2005.077, NPA.2005.174, NPA.2006.072, NPA.2006.076, NPA.2006.084, NPA.2006.097, NPA.2008.025, and NPA.2008.035.
In October 2023, Rachel Bernstein donated posters from commemorations for the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire created by the Remember the Triangle Fire Coalition; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2023.098.
Arrangement
Organized into two geographical series: I: United States; II: Other Countries--based on country of production of the posters. Folders within the United States series are arranged alphabetically by topic, and folders within the Other Countries series are arranged alphabetically by the name of the country of production, and then alphabetically by topic within each country.
Historical Note
The essential role of political posters in propaganda, recruitment, and sustaining morale has been well-documented in numerous books, exhibitions and catalogs, as have their striking graphic qualities and historical significance. They have been published by numerous parties, labor unions and federations, other organizations, entities, and individuals representing the entire spectrum of political affiliations and philosophies. Left and progressive organizations and artists, perhaps because the medium represents a chance to bypass the usual modes of communication and communicate outside of mainstream politics and power, have been particularly prolific in the production of posters.
Custodial History
Both individuals and organizations donated these posters to the Tamiment Library/ Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University. The earliest donations were made to the Tamiment Library when it was part of the Rand School for Social Science, a pioneer workers' school founded in New York City in 1906, and as a result of the close ties between the Rand School and the Socialist Party, this collection includes a significant grouping of Socialist Party posters. The core of the collection, however, is over one-thousand posters donated by Michael Roach, who acquired these items during the 1960s and 1970s, while managing a bookstore in Madison, Wisconsin.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Poster Collection (ALBA Graphics 001). Penina Coopersmith Collection on Student Radicalism (TAM 661).
Scope and Contents
The 2,165 posters and broadsides in the Tamiment/Wagner Poster and Broadside Collection relate to left-radicalism, progressive movements, labor unions and the counter-culture. Most were produced in the United States, but a significant number of posters on these same subjects from other countries are also included. Information on dates of individual items is scanty, but the approximate date-span for the collection is from 1904 to 2019, with the bulk of the material falling between 1970 and 1990.
U.S.-produced posters in the collection represent a broad range of left political parties, including the Communist Party of the United States, various Socialist parties, and some less well-known political organizations such as the American Labor Party, the Peace and Freedom Party, the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, and the Workers Party. Primary thematic subjects include: black power and civil rights (includes posters produced by or for the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee [SNCC], Black Panther Party, the Fort Hood soldiers, the Baraka Defense Committee, the Southern Christian Leadership Conference [SCLC], and the A. Philip Randolph Institute), the women's liberation movement (includes material on the struggle for the Equal Rights Amendment, the National Organization for Women, and women of color), Native American and gay liberation movements, anti-Vietnam War movements (includes posters on G.I. groups such as the Fort Dix 38, the Fort Jackson G.I.'s against the War and later, the Vietnam Veterans Against the War, other peace and disarmament movements, student protest (including posters produced by different factions of Students for a Democratic Society [SDS]), and the labor movement (represented by posters from a broad range of labor unions, and including boycotts such as those against grapes by the United Federation of Farm Workers, the Farah Pants boycott sponsored by the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the boycott against Trans World Airlines led by the Independent Federation of Flight Attendants). The collection also holds posters on more general topics such as housing and public transit that intersect with social and political issues, as well as a small group of posters that illustrate pro-Vietnam War, anti-radical and anti-labor points of view.
Among the earliest U.S. posters in the collection are a 1920 Presidential campaign poster for Eugene V. Debs, Socialist Party candidate (who ran while imprisoned in the Atlanta Federal Penitentiary for statements he had made opposing World War I), and a series designed by artist Ben Shahn for the federal Office of Price Administration during the Second World War on such issues as rent and price controls and rationing.
In addition to the United States, more than 30 countries are represented in the collection. Some of the largest groupings of non-U.S. posters come from the People's Republic of China, Cuba, the former Czechoslovak Republic, Great Britain, Spain, and Japan.
Most of the ca. 35 Spanish posters in the collection were produced by different (and sometimes opposing) leftist political parties, labor unions, and other organizations that supported the Spanish Republican government during Spain's Civil War from 1936 to 1938, including those issued by the anarchist-affiliated Consejo de la Escuela Nueva Unificada (CENU), Confederación Nacional del Trabajo (CNT), Federación Anarquista Ibérica (FAI), and Federación Ibérica de Juventudes Libertarias; the Socialist Partido Socialista Obrero Espagnol and Unión General de Trabajadores (UGT); and a Communist splinter party, Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista (POUM). Cuban posters in the collection were mostly produced by a Cuban government-sponsored organization: the Organizacion de la Solaridad de los Pueblos de Africa, Asia y Latinoamerica (OSPAAL). Most of the Czech posters in the collection were produced by the International Union of Students, a group sponsored by the government of the former Czechoslovak Republic, while those from the United Kingdom were produced mainly by the Poster Film Collective, a London-based political and cultural organization. Posters from these four organizations cover an extremely broad range of international issues. OSPAAL and OCLAE (Organización Continental Latinoamericana y Caribeña de Estudiantes) posters, for example, include those on the Cuban revolution, anti-imperialism, Nicaragua, El Salvador, Puerto Rico, Uruguay, Venezuela, and Vietnam; Chile, Peru, and Angola, and the Venceremos Brigade (an organization made up of American students recruited to assist in harvesting Cuba's sugar cane crop). Posters from the Poster Film Collective focus on the building of China under Mao Tse-Tung and anti-imperialist liberation struggles world-wide--particularly in Northern Ireland and Africa--and feature quotations from Marx, Engels, Lenin and Mao. Other posters from Great Britain include those promoting its Labour Party (both early original posters and later reproductions of early originals.
Other international holdings include posters from FRELIMO, the independence and liberation movement in Mozambique; from Japan on the subject of disarmament (many produced by the Peace Wave Action Committee); and from Communist Parties around the world, including France, Italy, the former Soviet Union, Cuba, Brazil, Germany, Mexico, and Czechoslovakia.
All posters (and the titles of the folders in which they are stored) have been assigned two primary classifications—first, a geographic classification corresponding to the country, continent, or region in which they were published (including now-defunct political entities, such as the Soviet Union, and broad geo-political regions such as Central America, the Middle East, and the Caribbean), and second, a broad topical heading based on their contents or theme and/or the artist or organization that produced it. Secondary subject headings have been assigned as appropriate, and country names may be used both for a poster's country of origin and as a topic. Where folder titles that include country or region names are followed by "general" this means that the posters they contain are concerned with issues that that have to do with the politics and problems of that country, while folder titles with country names followed by "non-[name of the country]" denote that the posters they contain, although produced in the named country, do not represent themes related to that country.
Since one item may often concern more than one subject, person, organization, in addition to the list of titles of folders that make up the container list for the collection, a cross-reference list that lists individual posters, follows. It is divided into four sections: names of organizations (including publications, titles of which are italicized), subjects, place names, and personal names (the person may be pictured, referred to, quoted, or the poster may have been produced by this person). Each poster has been assigned a unique individual number (which should be referenced when contacting the Tamiment Library for inquiries about specific posters, and used as part of citations and captions). Researchers are therefore advised to first locate the folder in which they may find a group of posters on a specific topic, and to consult the cross-reference list for additional specific posters on this (and allied) topics as well.
Please note that in addition to this finding aid, another important resource for using this collection is that more than three-quarters of the items in it are displayed online via the ARTstor website hosted by New York University's Bobst Library. This portion of the collection may be viewed by researchers affiliated with New York University by going to http://library.artstor.org/library/welcome.html and proceeding to "Browse -- Institutional Collections -- Tamiment/Wagner Poster and Broadside Collection," and may be searched by subject, artist, as well as by individual poster number. (Researchers not affiliated with NYU may view these images while onsite at the Tamiment Library only.)
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements.; Student movements.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Anti-imperialist movements.; Communist parties; Labor movement.; Labor unions; Political posters, American.; Political posters, Chinese.; Political posters, Cuban.; Political posters, Czech.; Political posters, Russian.; Political prisoners -- Spain; Socialist parties.; Posters.; Protest movements.; Workers Party (1940-1949); Communist Party of the United States of America; Peace Wave Action Committee; Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.); Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party; American Labor Party; Organizacion de la Solaridad de los Pueblos de Africa, Asia y Latinoamerica; Black Panther Party; National Organization for Women
- Series I: United States, undated
  - United States: About Africa, undated; US-1.0; 11 items (Flat-file-folder 3 Left)
    Ethiopia.; Zimbabwe.; Cuba.; Mozambique.; Namibia.; National Venceremos Brigade; SWAPO; Ethiopian Students Union in North America; Zimbabwe African National Liberation Army
  - United States: American Labor Party, undated; US-99.0; 16 items (Flat-file-folder 10)
    Transportation.; Civil rights.; Labor unions; Schools.; Housing.; Political campaigns.; Transport Workers Union of America; Workshop of Graphic Art (New York, N.Y.); Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954
  - United States: Anarchism, undated; US-83.0; 18 items (Flat-file-folder 9 Right)
    Labor unions; Political campaigns.; Unemployment.; Industrial Workers of the World
  - United States: About Angola, undated; US-2.0; 5 items (Flat-file-folder 2 Left)
    Youth Against War & Fascism; Movimento Popular de Libertação de Angola
  - United States: Animal Rights, undated; US-7.0; 1 item (Box 1)
  - United States: Anti-Apartheid, undated; US-8.0; 10 items (Flat-file-folder 14 Right)
    World War, 1939-1945.; South Africa; Namibia.
  - United States: Anti-Communist, undated; US-110.0; 2 items (Box 1)
  - United States: Anti-Fascist, undated; US-9.0; 3 items (Flat-file-folder 15 Right)
    Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
  - United States: Anti-Imperialism, undated; US-77.0; 5 items (Flat-file-folder 2 Left)
    Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Feminism; Black Workers Congress
  - United States: Anti-Nuclear, undated; US-10.0; 4 items (Flat-file-folder 16 Right)
    Health
  - United States: About Asia, undated; US-127.0; 2 items (Box 2)
    Japan.
  - United States: Black Power, undated; US-13.0; 20 items (Flat-file-folder 6 Left)
    South Africa; Ho, Chí Minh, 1890-1969; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); X, Malcolm, 1925-1965
  - United States: Black Power - Black Panther Party, undated; US-13.14; 28 items (Flat-file-folder 12)
    Prisoners and prisons.; Portraits.; Civil rights.; Cleaver, Eldridge, 1935-1998
  - United States: Boycotts, undated; US-14.0; 7 items (Flat-file-folder 3)
    Labor unions; Health; Performances.; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Pan-African Liberation Committee; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Labor Theater (New York, N.Y.)
  - United States: Boycotts - United Farm Workers (UFW), undated; US-14.1; 7 items (Flat-file-folder 4 Left)
    Industrial safety.; Labor unions
  - United States: About Central America, undated; US-73.0; 11 items (Flat-file-folder 2)
    Nicaragua.; South America.; El Salvador.; Disarmament.; Exhibitions.; Iran.; Health; Guatemala.; South Africa
  - United States: Children's Rights, undated; US-16.0; 1 item (Box 1)
  - United States: About Chile, undated; US-17.0; 10 items (Flat-file-folder 10 Left)
  - United States: Cities - New York City, undated; US-137.1; 2 items (Box 2)
  - United States: Civil Liberties, undated; US-19.0; 1 item (Box 1)
  - United States: Civil Rights, undated; US-18.0; 9 items (Flat-file-folder 6 Left)
    Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Unemployment.; Congress of Racial Equality; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
  - United States: Civil Rights-Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, undated; US-18.1; 6 items (Box 1)
    Political campaigns.
  - United States: Communist Party (US), undated; US-20.0; 14 items (Flat-file-folder 4)
    Labor unions; Puerto Rico.; Performances.; Unemployment.; Civil rights.; Political campaigns.; Darcy, Samuel, 1905-; Daily Worker (New York); Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Industrial Workers of the World; Ford, James W., 1893-1957; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-
  - United States: Communist Party (US)-International Labor Defense (ILD), undated; US-20.4; 1 item (Box 1)
    Darcy, Samuel, 1905-
  - United States: Communist Party (US)-International Workers Order, Inc., undated; US-20.2; 1 item (Box 1)
    Unemployment.; Health; World War, 1939-1945.
  - United States: Communist Party (US)- Morning Freiheit, undated; US-20.5; 1 item (Flat-file-folder 10)
    Performances.
  - United States: Counter Culture, undated; US-125.0; 1 item (Box 2)
  - United States: About Cuba, undated; US-21.0; 10 items (Box 1)
    Labor unions; National Venceremos Brigade; National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees
  - United States: Disarmament, undated; US-59.0; 30 items (Flat-file-folder 5, Flat-file-folder 9)
    Soviet Union.; Schools.; Political campaigns.; World War, 1939-1945.; Feminism; Labor unions; Workmen's Circle (U.S.); War Resisters League; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Mobilization for Survival (Organization); Coalition for a Nuclear-Free Harbor (New York, N.Y.); Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Union of Concerned Scientists; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; League for Industrial Democracy; Vladeck, B. (Baruch), 1886-1938; Young People's Socialist League
  - United States: Draft Resistance, undated; US-22.0; 11 items (Flat-file-folder 19 Right)
    El Salvador.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Prisoners and prisons.; Labor unions; Feminism; Black power.
  - United States: About El Salvador, undated; US-23.0; 14 items (Flat-file-folder 9 Right)
    Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Central America.; People's Anti-War Mobilization; Committee in Solidarity with the People of El Salvador (U.S.)
  - United States: Election Campaigns, undated; US-103.0; 15 items (Flat-file-folder 8 Left)
    Civil rights.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Labor unions
  - United States: Environment, undated; US-25.0; 2 items (Box 1)
    Disarmament.
  - United States: Exhibits, undated; US-12.0; 30 items (Flat-file-folder 2)
    El Salvador.; Labor unions; Anarchism.; Political campaigns.; Feminism; Unemployment.; Housing.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Black power.; Industrial safety.; France.; National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees; Industrial Workers of the World; Fasanella, Ralph; AFSCME; AFL-CIO; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - United States: Gay Liberation, undated; US-27.0; 9 items (Flat-file-folder 8)
  - United States: Generic Rhetoric and Quotations, undated; US-113.0; 15 items (Flat-file-folder 7 Left)
    Student movements.; Performances.; Civil rights.; Political campaigns.; Black power.; China; Mao, Zedong, 1893-1976
  - United States: Gulf War (1991), undated; US-139.0; 2 items (Box Shared Tamiment OS003)
  - United States: Housing, undated; US-29.0; 3 items (Flat-file-folder 20 Right)
  - United States: Humor and Satire, undated; US-115.0; 4 items (Flat-file-folder 7)
  - United States: Industrial Workers of the World (aka IWW aka Wobblies), undated; US-30.0; 15 items (Flat-file-folder 6)
    Draft resisters.; Music.; Labor unions; Women employees.; Industrial safety.
  - United States: International Human Rights Movement, undated; US-106.0; 2 items (Flat-file-folder 5 Left)
    El Salvador.
  - United States: About Iran, undated; US-31.0; 9 items (Flat-file-folder 7)
    Portraits.; Iranian Students Association of America
  - United States: Kentucky Miners' Defense, undated; US-32.0; 2 items (Box 1)
    Prisoners and prisons.; Civil rights.; Labor unions
  - United States: Labor Education, undated; US-130.0; 2 items (Box 2)
    Labor unions; Muste, A. J. (Abraham John), 1885-1967.; Brookwood Labor College (Katonah, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
  - United States: Labor History, undated; US-101.0; 21 items (Flat-file-folder 6)
    Labor unions; Feminism; Children's rights.; Unemployment.; Industrial Workers of the World
  - United States: Labor History -- Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire Commemoration Posters, 2011-2019 (Flat-file-folder 5)
  - United States: Labor History - UAW Education Department: "This Union Cause" Series, undated; US-101.1; 43 items (Box 1)
    Unemployment.; Labor unions; Children's rights.; Anarchism.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); AFL-CIO
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - Board of Delegates of the Building Trades of New York, 1897 (Box Shared Tamiment 065, Folder 2)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - Jewish Labor Committee, undated; US-54.7; 4 items (Box 1)
    Uruguay.; Poland; Israel.; France.
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), undated; US-54.2; 8 items (Flat-file-folder 13 Right)
    Unemployment.; International Longshoremen's Association
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - American Postal Workers Union (APWU), undated; US-54.3; 59 items (Box 1)
    Labor unions; Health; Unemployment.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; AFL-CIO
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), undated; US-54.4; 13 items (Flat-file-folder 14 Right)
    Political campaigns.; Unemployment.; World War, 1939-1945.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Industrial Workers of the World; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - general, undated; US-54.0; 40 items (Flat-file-folder 7)
    Technology.; Transportation.; Exhibitions.; Middle East.; Boycotts.; Child labor.; Performances.; Children's rights.; Health; Labor unions; Schools.; Industrial safety.; Union labels; World War, 1939-1945.; Professional Air Traffic Controllers Organization (Washington, D.C.); United Farm Workers of America; National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees; Shahn, Ben, 1898-1969; Chavez, Cesar, 1927-1993; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Transport Workers Union of America; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Committee of Interns and Residents (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; United Federation of Teachers; Communications Workers of America
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - Justice for Hamlet--Save the South Coalition, 1992-05-02 (Folder Shared Tamiment 109)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - New York City Central Labor Council, undated; US-54.5; 13 items (Box 1)
    Labor unions
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - "Organizing--It's Our Job", circa 20th century (Folder Shared Tamiment 109)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - "Strike Relief", circa 20th century (Folder Shared Tamiment 109)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - Textile Workers of America (TWUA), undated; US-54.8; 7 items (Box 1)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), undated; US-54.6; 25 items (Box 1)
    World War, 1939-1945.; Transportation.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations - TWA Flight Attendants for Justice & Dignity in the Workplace, 1986; US-54.0-2 (Folder Shared Tamiment 109)
  - United States: Labor Unions and Labor Organizations, miscellaneous, undated; US-54.1; 7 items (Flat-file-folder 16 Right)
    World War, 1939-1945.; Labor unions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Child labor.; Transportation.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Civil Service Technical Guild; United Federation of Teachers; Communications Workers of America
  - United States: Liberal Party, undated; US-116.0; 1 item (Box 2)
  - United States: Marijuana, undated; US-33.0; 4 items (Box 1)
    Health; Prisoners and prisons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Civil rights.